SEBASTIAN VARELA BENITEZ

214 Bridlerange Place SW | Calgary AB, Canada, T2Y 0K9 | Cell: 1.403.805.9207 svarelab@ucalgary.ca

PROFILE

Passionate and well-rounded individual graduating in Mechanical Engineering this May. Pursuing a challenging and goal driven work environment. Have 13-months of plant and office-based engineering experience with General Electric and three years with FSAE Schulich Racing team as the Lead Suspension Engineer.

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Science in Mechanical Engineering Minor in Mechatronics University of Calgary – Calgary, Alberta Cumulative GPA: 3.41

EXTRACURRICULAR

Lead Suspension Engineer: University of Calgary Schulich Racing FSAE; Calgary, Alberta

Sept 2016 - Present

 Managed the progression of eight projects for the suspension sub-team while maintaining a high GPA with a full course load

Expected graduation: May 2018

- Experience with full lifecycle of developing the suspension system; including the project proposal, design calculations, prototyping, manufacturing and assembly
- Compiled the suspension system portion of the cost report and design specification report for the Lincoln 2017 FSAE competition (Ranked 1st out of 73 universities for cost report)
- Designed bearing holders and suspension linkages that were utilized in the SR18 race car that competed in the Lincoln 2017 FSAE competition (Ranked best Canadian team at competition)
- Provided technical support and guidance to new members of the team as they adjusted to a fast-paced environment to ensure a cohesive team

Suspension Team Member: University of Calgary Schulich Racing FSAE; Calgary, Alberta Sept 2015 – Sept 2016

- Managed a steep learning curve regarding team policies, processes, and procedures
- Optimized vehicle suspension linkage design through multiple iterations while keeping time, cost, weight and manufacturing considerations into account
- Performed multiple failure analysis studies by utilizing engineering and finite element analysis principles for stress analysis, in parallel with Computer Aided Design software for 3D modelling
- Presented design progress and benefits to team lead through constant communication and clear reports, as well as to full executive team and alumni through comprehensive presentations

SKILL HIGHLIGHTS

- Three years experience with designing vehicle dynamics and complete manufacturing process of vehicle components
- Strong analytical skills and problem-solving methodologies, able to confidently apply engineering principles
- Experienced with CAD modeling and stress simulations (Solidworks), and engineering drawings (AutoCAD)
- Proficient creating comprehensive reports and project schedules with MS Office Suite (including MS Project)
- Proven project management skills in both university and industry environments. Have experience working with clients and meeting project schedule and budget deliverables
- Excellent written and interpersonal skills, Bilingual (English and Spanish)

SEBASTIAN VARELA BENITEZ

214 Bridlerange Place SW | Calgary AB, Canada, T2Y 0K9 | Cell: 1.403.805.9207 svarelab@ucalgary.ca

WORK EXPERIENCE

Lead Technical Specialist Intern: General Electric (GE); Stoney Creek, Ontario

July 2016-August 2017

- Created and updated comprehensive cost reports and schedules for multiple projects simultaneously
- Compiled Variable Cost Productivity (VCP) Project packages containing cost and return on investment calculations to justify funding for projects. (Contributed to total of \$500K CAD of recognized VCP savings)
- Trained two new employees in position responsibilities while performing daily tasks by effectively delegating tasks throughout the training period and by creating documentation as a guide on different procedures
- Adapted to a fast-paced environment in an industry that demanded consistent improvements on key business measurements such as customer satisfaction, quality, delivery and profit
- Led project cost reviews with GE's finance department and did monthly presentations to 40 hourly staff to inform them about the quarterly financials, safety metric updates and VCP updates
- Monitored inventory for shop supplies and compiled a summary report used to order material accordingly
- Optimized excel reports through automation using formulas and basic Macros, increasing productivity

VOLUNTEER EXPERIENCE

ESS Peer Mentorship Program: University of Calgary; Calgary, Alberta

Sept 2017 - Present

- Took on a first-year engineering student as a mentee with the goal of providing continuous guidance during the transition period of the first year of university
- Providing a helping hand with stressful situations and providing tips that will increase the success of the mentee

Orientation Leader: University of Calgary; Calgary, Alberta

Aug 28th - Sep 4th 2015

- Regularly developed and utilized public speaking skills during the campus tours and large group activities
- Participated in training that included bystander intervention and group-based activities
- Represented the University of Calgary as an ambassador to 20 first-year students
- Provided guidance and facilitated team-bonding activities for the first-year students
- Developed team-work and communication skills while working with other orientation leaders